James J. Pirkl Papers
James J. Pirkl Papers
1936-2008
Pirkl, James J. (James Joseph), 1930-
75 linear ft.
Papers of the American industrial designer, pioneer in transgenerational design and disability issues. Retired in 1992 as Chair of the Dept. of Design, Syracuse University, where he had taught since 1965. Collection includes correspondence, blueprints, drawings, and client files.
149708
Biographical History
James J. Pirkl (1930- ) is an award-winning American industrial designer and educator, known particularly for his work in transgenerational design.
Born in Nyack, New York, Pirkl graduated from Pratt Institute’s Advertising Design program (1951) and went on to earn his BID cum laude in industrial design (1958). He joined the General Motors Design Staff as a junior designer, rising to senior project designer responsible for the design of the "Avenue of Progress" section of the General Motors Futurama pavilion at the 1964 New York World's Fair. Subsequently promoted to assistant chief designer of Frigidaire's Advanced Product Research Studio, he was recruited by Syracuse University and appointed assistant professor of industrial design in 1965. Promoted to associate professor in 1970 and full professor in 1974, he was named professor-in-charge of industrial design in 1978 and served as department chair from 1985 until his retirement as Professor Emeritus in 1993.
In addition to his academic responsibilities he served as an industrial design consultant to a wide range of organizations both in the United States and overseas, including Age Wave, Inc., the Arthritis Foundation, Asahikasei Homes Co. (Japan), The Boeing Company, Design Age (London), Ford Motor Design Center, General Electric, Johnson & Johnson, McNeil Consumer Products, the National Association of Home Builders, and Xerox Corporation. He also collaborated on design projects with such notable industrial designers as George A. Beck, Arthur Crapsey, Mark Harrison, Arthur J. Pulos, and Robert G. Smith. In 1976, under the sponsorship of the U.S. State Department, he was one of five American industrial design educators invited to conduct seminars on industrial design education at the All (Soviet) Union Research Institute of Industrial Design (VNITTE) in Moscow, USSR, and again in 1978 at The Bauhaus in Dessau, East Germany.
Pirkl is the founding director of Transgenerational Design Matters, a design consultancy for the 50+ market, and has been described as a "key figure in universal design" by the Smithsonian's Cooper-Hewitt Design Museum. He is widely acknowledged as the father of "transgenerational design," a term he coined and defined in 1984 as "the practice of making products and environments compatible with those physical and sensory impairments associated with human aging and which limit major activities of daily living." In 2003, AARP's The Magazine featured his Transgenerational House project's pioneering design concepts.
He is a frequent lecturer and presenter in the U.S. and abroad, and his articles appear in numerous international journals and periodicals. He is the co-author of Guidelines and Strategies for Designing Transgenerational Products (1988), and his Transgenerational Design: Products for an Aging Population, received a 1994 Gold Industrial Design Excellence Award.
A member of the Industrial Designers Society of America (IDSA) since 1972, Pirkl served as a board member, regional vice president, and chairman of its Central New York Chapter. He also chaired IDSA's Education Committee, its first Universal Design Committee, and the Accreditation Council, which, in 1984, established the first school evaluation and accreditation agreement between IDSA and NASAD (the National Association of Schools of Art and Design). IDSA named him a Fellow in 1985 and in 2001 presented him with the Society's esteemed Education Award. He is a life member of the Human Factors and Ergonomics Society, the Authors Guild, and the National Association of Schools of Art and Design.
Presently (2009) James J. Pirkl lives in Albuquerque, New Mexico with his wife, Sarah, and their three children.
[Biographical sketch provided by James J. Pirkl, 2009.]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The James J. Pirkl Papers consists of personal files, project files, scholarly works, subject files, Syracuse University Department of Design files, writing and speaking materials, and a small amount of miscellaneous. Folder titles are given as received from the donor.
Personal files includes biographical sketches and resumes, citations of Pirkl's work, a diary from a trip to France in 1967, photographs, and magazine articles. There are also sketches, blueprints and printed material relating to Pirkl's designs for General Motors, and material relating to the World Design Foundation.
Projects consists primarily of files relating to Pirkl's Transgenerational House project, including plans, sketches, photographs, and letterhead. Also in this series are three years' of judges' manuals for the Tylenol Arthritis Foundation's Industrial Design Student Innovation Excellence Awards (1994, 1995, 1996), and some material relating to the Universal Design Summit in 2006.
Scholarly works includes correspondence, presentations, proposals, press releases and other formats. The bulk of this series consists of working files for Pirkl's book, Transgenerational Design: Products for an Aging Population (1997), for which he won a Gold Industrial Design Excellence Award (IDEA) award.
Subject files cover a wide range of organizations, projects, activities, and topics related to transgenerational design. Folders contain a mixture of formats, including agendas, clippings, correspondence, itineraries, notes, programs, publications and reports, as well as in some cases drafts or final copies of addresses, lectures, presentations, papers and workshops by Pirkl. Scattered throughout are a few papers by others, including Armand Winfield and Arthur Pulos.
Syracuse University Department of Design materials date from Pirkl's tenure as chair of the department, and contains correspondence, meeting notes, course notes, samples of student work, and other items.
Writing and speaking contains notes, drafts and final version of speeches, addresses, papers, and other presentations from conferences, meetings, seminars, and other venues, both in the United States and international.
Three folders of catalogs, filed under Miscellaneous, complete the collection.
There is also a substantial amount of as-yet-unprocessed material. This material is not yet open for research.
Arrangement of the Collection
Series and folder titles and contents were retained as received from the donor; as a result, material relating to a given topic (e.g. the Tylenol Arthritis Foundation) may be found in several different locations. Writing and speaking files are arranged chronologically, as received from the donor. The remainder of the series have been arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
has the papers of a number of important industrial designers and companies. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Industrial Design; Transgenerational Design Matters (Organization); Pirkl, James J. (James Joseph), 1930-; Older consumers -- United States.; Aging -- United States.; Design, Industrial.; Educators -- United States.; People with disabilities -- United States.; Consumers with disabilities -- United States.; Industrial designers -- United States.; Educators.; Industrial designers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Personal
  - Bio / resumes, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Citations from works by James J. Pirkl (Box 1)
  - Citations in MFA thesis, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Clippings of students' work, etc., 1960s-70s (Box 1)
  - Diary from France trip, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Form paper, design notes, etc., 1970s (Box 2)
  - General Motors
    - Historical material (Box 2)
    - Pirkl designs, etc., 1960s (Box 2)
    - Pirkl designs, etc. (Map-case 102)
    - GM Futurama - 1964 World's Fair drafts, 1960s (Box 2)
  - Photographs, miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Pratt Institute / Wayne State University, 1957-1958 (Box 3)
    See also Subject files: Pratt Institute
  - Who's Who Updates (Box 3)
  - World Design Foundation, 1995-1996 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous magazine articles (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Projects
  - Transgenerational House
    - Proposal to Maytag Corporation, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Background memorandum, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Preliminary plans (Box 4)
    - Stationery (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous sketches (Box 4)
    - Description and PR material (Box 4)
    - Photographs
      - Final grading and stucco (Box 4)
      - Framing and interior (Box 4)
      - Concrete slab, concrete/stucco (Box 4)
      - Pool construction (Box 4)
  - Tylenol Arthritis Foundation
    - Industrial Design Student Innovation Excellence Awards, 1994-1996; judges' manual; 3 folders (Box 5)
      See also Subject files: Age Wave and Rowland Company
    - Design Awards, Consumer Products nominations, 1995 (Box 5)
  - Universal Design Summit 2, 2006 (Box 5)
- Scholarly works
  - Planning Commission, Cazenovia, NY, 1988-93 (Box 6)
  - Research / support / proposals, 1976-2006 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1990-2008; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Preliminary drafts (Box 6)
  - Reports, addresses, presentations, 1985-1987 (Box 6)
  - Reports, addresses, presentations, 1987-2000; 5 folders (Box 7)
  - Design Management Journal article, 1991 (Box 7)
  - IDSA Innovation article, 1991 (Box 7)
  - Kohlbacher book chapter, 2007 (Box 7)
  - Press releases (Box 8)
  - Transgenerational Design book
    - Charts (Box 8)
    - Drafts, 1991-1994; 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Final art (Box 8)
    - Daily memo book, 1994-1999 (Box 8)
    - Guidelines and Strategies flier, 6 copies (Box 9)
    - Design research material, miscellaneous (Box 9)
    - John Wiley & Sons (Box 9)
    - PBC International (Box 9)
    - Rockport (Box 9)
    - Outlines (Box 9)
    - Appendix (Box 9)
    - Draft notes (Box 9)
    - Permissions (Box 9)
    - Research data (Box 9)
    - PR (Box 9)
- Subject files
  - Age Wave '95
    - General (Box 10)
    - Georgia Tech (Box 10)
    - Long Beach (Box 10)
    - Rochester Institute of Technology (RIT) (Box 10)
    - San Jose (Box 10)
  - Age Wave '96 (Box 10)
  - Age Wave '97 (Box 10)
  - Aging (Box 10)
  - American Association of Museums (Box 10)
  - American Association of Retired People (AARP) (Box 10)
  - American Institute of Architects (AIA) (Box 11)
  - American Institute of Building Design (AIBD) (Box 11)
  - American Society on Aging (ASA) (Box 11)
  - Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA) (Box 11)
  - Appliance Manufacturing Association (Box 11)
  - Arthritis Foundation (Box 11)
  - Aston, Judith (Box 11)
  - Author's Guild, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Barr, Charles (Box 11)
  - Bayer (Box 11)
  - Beck, Ben, regarding Dale Beck (Box 11)
  - Beck, Guy (Box 11)
  - Bhaskaran, Lakshmi (Box 12)
  - Blaich, Robert I. (Box 12)
  - Boeing (Box 12)
  - BOLT (Box 12)
  - Brownlie Design (Box 12)
  - Business / management (Box 12)
  - Center for Universal Design, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Chavez, Dennis (Senator), See Cordova, John
  - Chrysler (Box 12)
  - Cleminshaw, Doug (Box 12)
  - Coleman, Roger (Box 12)
  - Cooper Hewitt (Box 12)
  - Copley Publishing (Box 12)
  - Copyright (Box 12)
  - Cordova, John (Box 13)
  - Crucible Steel, Solvay, NY, See McCrone, Jeffrey
  - Cultural Resources Council (Box 13)
  - Davis, Bruce (Box 13)
  - Dementia / Alzheimers (Box 13)
  - Design for Aging (Box 13)
  - Design Management Institute (Box 13)
  - Domus Academy (Box 13)
  - Elder market (Box 13)
  - Elkay Manufacturing (Box 13)
  - Environment (Box 13)
  - Ergonomic Logic, Inc. (Box 13)
  - Falls / falling (Box 13)
  - Ford Motor Design Center (Box 13)
  - Frost & Sullivan (Box 13)
  - Future issues (Box 13)
  - Gantz, Carroll (Box 13)
  - General Electric (Box 14)
  - Gerontological Society of America (Box 14)
  - Glasgow School of Art (Box 14)
  - Grossette interview (Box 14)
  - Handicap issues (Box 14)
  - Health (Box 14)
  - Hearing (Box 14)
  - Hewlett-Packard (Box 14)
  - High Tech (Box 14)
  - Hoyer, William, paper on cognition (Box 14)
  - Human aging (Box 14)
  - Human factors / economics (Box 14)
  - ICSID, "Design for the elderly" (Box 14)
  - IDEA Gold Award, to Pirkl, 1994 (Box 14)
  - IEEE special issue, 1986 (Box 15)
  - ID Magazine (Box 15)
  - Independence (Box 15)
  - Industrial Design Society of America (IDSA)
    - General (Box 15)
    - Design History Section (Box 15)
    - National Schools of Art and Design (NASAD) Liaison Committee (Box 15)
    - National meeting, 1995 (Box 15)
    - Transgenerational and Disabilities Committee (Box 15)
  - International Society for Occupational Ergonomics and Safety (Box 15)
  - Independence Builders (Box 15)
  - Jobs / employment (Box 15)
  - Junior League (Box 15)
  - Juvenile Product Manufacturing Association, 1990 (Box 15)
  - Kitchen appliances (Box 15)
  - Kohler Company (Box 15)
  - Koncelik, Joseph (Box 15)
  - Konturi (Germany) (Box 16)
  - Kodak (Box 16)
  - K-Z Associates, Inc. (Box 16)
  - KUNM-FM (Box 16)
  - Live Oak Editions (Charles Little) (Box 16)
  - Lochner, Wendy (Box 16)
  - Lonczak, John (Box 16)
  - Machine design (Box 16)
  - Marketing (Box 16)
  - McCrone, Jeffrey (Box 16)
  - Mentoring (Box 16)
  - Metropolitan State College (Box 16)
  - Museum of Modern Art (Box 16)
  - Myths of aging (Box 16)
  - Nabisco (Box 16)
  - National Association of Home Builders, Senior Housing Research, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - National Association of Schools of Art and Design (NASAD)
    - General (Box 16)
    - IDSA accreditation (Box 17)
    - Publications, reports to members, briefing papers, miscellaneous other publications (Box 17)
  - National Broadcasting Corporation (NBC) (Box 17)
  - National Endowment for the Arts (NEA) (Box 17)
  - National New Deal Preservation Association (NNDPA) (Box 17)
  - National Public Radio (NPR) (Box 17)
    See also Writing and speaking: National: National Public Radio interview
  - New Mexico State University, The Institute for Gerontological Research and Education (TIGRE) (Box 17)
  - Nursing homes (Box 17)
  - Packaging, See Warner & Finley
  - Pan American Round Table (Box 17)
  - Pearl River High School (Box 17)
  - Poole, Janet (University of New Mexico) (Box 17)
  - Peachtree Doors and Windows (Box 17)
  - Pratt Institute (Box 17)
    See also Personal: Pratt Institute / Wayne State University
  - Prince (Box 18)
  - Procter and Gamble (Box 18)
  - Pro Matura Group
    - General (Box 18)
    - Awards judging, 1995-1996 (Box 18)
  - Pulos, Arthur, includes several papers by Pulos, parodies of Christmas carols, other writings (Box 18)
  - Ralph Lauren (Box 18)
  - Raschko, Bettyann (Box 18)
  - Rehabilitation (Box 18)
  - Rehabilitation Engineering and Assistive Technology Society of North America (RESNA) (Box 18)
  - Retirement (Box 18)
  - Rickard, Paul (Box 18)
  - Rowland Company (Box 18)
  - Royal Society for the Encouragement of the Arts (RSA) (Box 18)
  - Salmen, John (Box 18)
  - Seating (Box 18)
  - Sekulski, Ronald (Box 18)
  - Seniors Research Group (Box 18)
  - Sixbey, Friedman, Leedom & Ferguson (Box 18)
  - Smart House (Box 19)
  - Statistics (Box 19)
  - Steinfeld, Edward (Box 19)
  - Strategies (Box 19)
  - Stress (Box 19)
  - Sunlight Homes (Box 19)
  - Transgenerational products / problems (Box 19)
  - Transportation (Box 19)
  - Transportation Research Board (Box 19)
  - Universal Design (Box 19)
  - University of New Mexico (Box 19)
  - Vision (Box 19)
  - Warner & Finley (Box 19)
  - Whirlpool (Box 19)
  - Winfield, Armand, includes paper by Winfield (Box 19)
- Syracuse University Department of Design
  - Chair evaluation, 1990-1991 (Box 20)
  - Chair search, 1981-1982 (Box 20)
  - Correspondence, 1965-1991; 3 folders (Box 20)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1965-1990; 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Form originals (Box 20)
  - Gerontology / Walter Beattie (Box 21)
  - Graduate Students, miscellaneous, 1992-1993 (Box 21)
  - Independent Study Degree Program, 1973 (Box 21)
  - News clippings, 1965-2000; 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Research project, 1981 (Box 21)
  - Smith Hall renovation, 1991 (Box 21)
  - Student papers (Box 21)
  - Student projects (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous SU publications (Box 21)
  - SU, miscellaneous (Box 22)
  - Design Department, miscellaneous (Box 22)
- Writing and speaking
  - National
    - SU seminar, "Closing the Gap", 1975 (Box 22)
    - New York State Industrial Arts Convention, 1981 (Box 22)
    - IDSA accreditation, 1983 (Box 22)
    - The Aging Human Factor (Conference), 1984 (Box 22)
    - NASAD Annual Meeting Presentation, 1986 (Box 22)
    - Technology & Aging Conference, 1989 (Box 22)
    - NY State Society on Aging Conference, 1989 (Box 22)
    - American Society on Aging Conference, 1990 (Box 22)
    - IDSA NationalDesign Education Conference, 1990 (Box 22)
    - IDSA Southern District Conference, 1990 (Box 22)
    - Transgenerational Design Conference, 1990 (Box 22)
    - Ohio Governor's Conference on Aging, 1991 (Box 22)
    - Arizona State University Lecture, 1991 (Box 23)
    - International Management Council Conf., 1991 (Box 23)
    - Conference on Design Education, 1991 (Box 23)
    - IDSA Educator's Conference, 1992 (Box 23)
    - ADA Education Seminar, 1992 (Box 23)
    - Universal Design Conference, 1992 (Box 23)
    - American Society on Aging article, 1994 (Box 23)
    - RISD Universal Kitchen Project, 1996 (Box 23)
    - Universal Design Conference, 1998 (Box 23)
    - Design Education Conference, 1998 (Box 23)
    - Family Life Conference, Dakota Weslean U., 1998 (Box 24)
    - Unlimited by Design Exhibit, Cooper/Hewitt, 1998 (Box 24)
    - STEMPE Technical Meeting Address, 1999 (Box 24)
    - National Public Radio Interview, 1999 (Box 24)
    - Universal Design Conference, 2000; 2 folders (Box 24)
    - Protection & Advocacy System, 2005 (Box 24)
    - WITHIT Conference, 2006; keynote address (Box 24)
    - American River College, 2006; address (Box 24)
    - IDSA/Human Factors Society Conference, 2007 (Box 24)
    - IDSA/ICSID World Design Congress, 2007; address (Box 25)
    - Kendal at Ithaca, 2008; address (Box 25)
  - International
    - All-Union Research Institute, USSR (Box 25)
    - Inter national Symposium on Art and Design, 1981 (Box 25)
    - ICSID Interdesign, Norway, 1989 (Box 25)
    - China Industrial Design Congress, Taiwan, 1990 (Box 25)
    - Wuhan International Symposium on Industrial Design, China, 1991 (Box 25)
    - KAIST Accreditation Evaluation, Korea, 1992; 2 folders (Box 25)
    - Design Age: Royal College of Art, London, 1993 (Box 25)
    - Netherlands Design Institute, Amsterdam, 1995 (Box 26)
    - Design Age: Royal College of Art, London, 1995; 2 folders (Box 26)
    - International Guest Lecture Series, 1995
      - General (Box 26)
      - Amsterdam (Box 26)
      - Dublin (Box 26)
      - Einhoven (Box 26)
      - Helsinki (Box 26)
      - London (Box 26)
    - Design for Aging Network (DAN), 1995; 2 folders (Box 27)
    - Design für die Zunkunft, chapter, 1997 (Box 27)
    - International Seminar on Technology, Brazil, 2000 (Box 27)
    - Ozone Design Center, Tokyo, 2000; 2 folders (Box 27)
    - 4th World Aging & Generations Congress, Switzerland, 2007 (Box 27)
- Miscellaneous
  - Catalogs, 3 folders (Box 13)